我们将谈谈函数建模。
We're gonna talk a little bit about function modeling.
让我们跳到函数上。
Let's hop over to functions.
嘟嘟嘟嘟嘟嘟。
Doo doo doo doo doo doo.
让我们看看如何让自己开始。
Let's see what to get myself to start.
谢谢你，布莱恩。
Thank you, Brian.
从一无所有开始真是太好了。
That's very nice to start off with nothing.
好的，所以 [笑] 所以我们只是用验证进行了函数建模。
Okay, so [LAUGH] so we just did function modeling with validations.
有人抓到了吗？
Did anybody catch that?
我们说，我要去，而不是建模一种数据，
We said, I'm going to, instead of modeling a type of data and
该类型中的数据，我要建模一个函数。
the data inside that type, I'm gonna model a function.
我们将其称为运行，然后我们就可以组合功能。
We're gonna call it run, and then we're able to combine functions.
所以让我们多谈一点。
So let's talk about that a little bit more.
给自己一些函数，我最喜欢的，toUpper，其实我应该
Let's give ourself some functions, my favorite ones, toUpper, actually I should
可能只是引入了 rammed 或其他东西，但没关系，x 到大写。
probably just bring in rammed or something but it's fine, x to UpperCase.
好吧，其他最喜欢的函数惊呼我们只做 x concat，
All right, and other favorite function exclaimed we'll just do x concat,
[笑] 我们走了。
[LAUGH] there we go.
然后让我们看看还有什么，应该没问题。
And then let's see what else, should be fine.
好的，所以我们在这里尝试做的是使用这些函数
Okay, so what we're trying to do here is take these functions and
假设我想组合它们并以不同的方式组合它们。
let's say I want to combine them and compose them in different ways.
我想为它们建模并与它们一起做有趣的事情。
I want to model them and do interesting things with them.
函数没有给你任何关于它的方法。
Function doesn't give you any methods on it.
所以我们实际上可以做的是 make 函数。
So what we could do is actually make function.
这需要一些，我将称之为运行和运行，我们将公开它。
And that takes some, which I'm gonna call run and run we'll expose that.
所以我们实际上可以运行它。
So we can actually run it.
让我们从做一个 concat 开始。
Let's just start by doing a concat.
因为我们刚刚使用过幺半群。
Because we've just worked with monoids.
我们刚刚从那开始。
We're just fresh from that.
所以如果我想连接两个函数，我该怎么做？
So if I want to concat two functions, how would I do that?
嗯，我还有一个功能。
Well, I have another function.
我会打电话给 other.run。
And I'll call other.run.
我知道我跑了。
And I know I have my run.
我必须运行该函数以获取值。
And I have to run the function to get the value out.
然后我连接另一个给我的值，对吗？
And then I concat the value that the other one gave me, right?
但它必须关闭，我必须返回新函数，
But it have to be closed, I have to return new function,
如果我组合两个函数，我必须返回一个函数。
if I'm combining two functions I have to return a function.
所以我们将从那里开始，我们将从功能开始。
So we'll start there, we'll start with function.
嘿，看，函数需要一个参数。
And hey, look, function takes an argument.
现在突然有了一个x，
Now all of a sudden have an x,
不知从哪儿冒出来的，我们现在只有一个 x，是不是很整洁？
out of nowhere, we just have an x now, isn't that neat?
我明白了。
I get that passed in.
所以现在我可以用 x 运行我的另一个。
So now I can run my other one with x.
用 x 记住我的函数，我可以连接结果。
Remember my function with x, and I can concat the results.
太棒了。
That is cool.
有人对此有任何疑问吗？
Does anybody have any questions on that?
这正是我们刚刚对验证所做的。
That's exactly what we just did with validations.
有趣的是连接
And what's interesting about this is concating
两个函数说我有两个盒子。
two functions says I have two boxes.
你可以把函数看作一个因素，我认为我们可以正式地把它变成一个因素，
You can think of functions as a factor, I think we can formally make it a factor,
让我们这样做。
let's do that.
现在，让我们将 f 映射到我们的函数上。
Now, let's map f over our function.
所以你总是把它放回盒子里，得到一个 x，在 x 上运行它，我们得到一个值。
So you always keep it back in the box, get an x, run it on the x, we get a value.
我们对该值运行 f 。
And we run f on that value.
现在我们有了一个因素，对吧？
And now we have a factor, right?
Run 会返回一个值，你可以把它想象成一个盒子
Run is gonna return us a value, function you can think of as a box holding
一个值，您必须运行它来获取该值，然后我们对其运行 f。
a value and you have to run it to get the value and then we run f on it.
所以我要去的地方是我们有
So where I was going with that is is we have
这些组合函数的方式，map只是一个函数的组合。
these ways to combine functions, map is just a composition on a function.
concat 说两者都运行，然后合并结果。
And concat says run both and then combine the results.
我拿着这个东西，就像直觉告诉所有其他人一样
I'm holding this thing and just like the intuition says from all the other
例如，我会打开我的盒子并连接里面的东西。
examples, I'll open up my box and concat what's inside.
所以，当我们谈论函数时，盒子示例有点崩溃，因为
So, the box example kind of breaks down when we're talking about functions because
你并没有真正将函数视为一个盒子，但我猜你可以。
you don't really think of functions as a box but, you can I guess.
所以让我们对 upper 和
So let's do function to upper and
我们将把它和它的函数 exclaim 结合起来。
we'll concat that with its function exclaim.
好的，太好了。
All right, great.
然后我们将使用 fp sux 运行它。
And then we'll run that with a fp sux.
好吧[笑]。
All right [LAUGH].
好吧，没有函数建模零。
All right, no function modelling zero.
好的，那么这里发生了什么？
Okay, so what happened here?
第一个 UpperCase 它返回一个字符串。
The first one UpperCase it returned a string.
由于字符串是一个半群或一个幺半群，我们将它连接起来。
And since strings a semigroup or a monoid, we concat it.
我们将它与运行另一个的结果连接起来。
We concatt it with the result of running the other one.
有趣的。
Interesting.
所以我们已经运行了两个函数并且我们已经整理了结果。
So we've run two functions and we've concacted the results.
我可以做一些我们把它们放在一个数组中的事情
I could do something where we put them in an arrays and
我们会得到结果的数组等等。
we'll get the arrays of the results and so on.
但这开始形成我们所谓的读者单子的基础。
But this is starting to form the basis of what we call the reader monad.
我们实际上是在对一个函数本身进行建模，如果我们对其进行映射，让我们这样做。
We're actually modeling a function itself and if we map over it, let's do this.
让我们映射结果，现在这个拉号是多少，对吧？
Let's map over the result, which is this pull number now, right?
然后我们无论如何，从前几片中切下一片，三片。
And then we'll whatever, take a slice of the first couple slice, three.
那样有用吗？
Does that work?
好吧，酷。
All right, cool.
所以我们能够映射结合这两个函数的结果。
So we're able to map over the result of combining these two functions.
然后，我们运行它。
And then, we run it on that.
那么，它是什么？
So, what is it?
使函数成为 monad 是什么意思？
What does it mean to make function a monad?
那意味着什么？
What would that mean?
单子谈论嵌套，对吧？
Monads talk about nesting, right?
所以我们会说，我在一个函数中有一个函数，对吗？
So we'd say, I have a function within a function, right?
每个函数都有一些参数，对，这需要一个 y。
Each function takes some argument, right, and this takes a y.
我们现在这里有一个 x 和 ay。
We have an x and a y here now.
我们想将这两个扁平化为一个函数。
We wanna flatten these two into one function.
这就是 monad 所做的。
That's what monads do.
所以，让我们写吧。
So, let's write that.
看看这里发生了什么。
See what happens here.
所以我们有链到链 F。
So we have chain to chain F.
将会发生的是我们需要在外部返回一个函数。
And what's gonna happen is we need to return a function on the outside.
这样做的原因很好，我们可以看看，如果我刚刚决定
And the reason for that is well, we could just see, if I just decided
要运行我的函数，我什至没有 x 来运行它。
to run my function, I don't even have an x to run it with.
那行不通。
That doesn't work.
[笑] 所以我必须首先说好的，但功能需要一个 x，对。
[LAUGH] So I have to start by saying okay, but function it's gonna take an x, right.
然后我将使用 x 运行我的函数。
And then I'll run my function with the x.
我们说好的，就像地图一样，
And we are saying okay, just like map,
我想打电话给 f，对。
I want to call f on that, right.
将运行我的函数的值传递给下一个函数。
Pass the value of running my function into the next function.
在我们进一步了解它的含义之前，这可能会有所帮助。
Maybe it's helpful before we go any further to see what it means.
所以假设我要使用另一个函数链接到 upper，所以
So let's say I am going to chain to upper with another function, so
我们得到我们的 UpperCase upper，然后我要返回另一个函数，对吧？
we get our UpperCase upper, and then I'm gonna return another function, right?
那确实惊呼，哎呀，我在鞋面上拼错了。
That does exclaim on, oops, I spelled it wrong on the upper.
让我们看看，这需要
And let's see, this takes a y and
我想它现在对它没有任何作用。
I guess it just doesn't do anything with it right now.
我们会弄清楚如何处理这个 y 但是
We'll figure out what to do with this y but
我们还有另一个论点，这就是重点。
we have another argument, that's kind of the point.
我们只是凭空而来。
We just have this y out of nowhere.
所以让我们让它工作，然后我们会看看这里发生了什么。
So let's get this to work and then we'll kind of look at what's happening here.
这么高，好吧，所以
So high, all right, so
我们在这件事上，我们运行了这个函数，我们得到了另一个函数，然后
we're in this thing, we ran the function, we got another function out and
我们现在必须运行那个函数，对吗？
we actually have to run that function now, right?
再次说出 x，看看那里会发生什么。
With, say the x again and see what happens there.
所以让我们继续玩这个游戏。
So let's go ahead and play through this one.
看看会发生什么，我们就会变得很酷，
See what happens and we get high cool,